When you're learning a new idea, for
example a new vocabulary word or
a new concept, or
a new problem-solving approach,
you sometimes tend to practice it over and
over again during the same study session.
A little of this is useful and
necessary but continuing to study or
practice after you've mastered what you
can in the session is called overlearning.
Overlearning can have its place.
It can help produce an automaticity
that can be important when you're
executing a serve in tennis or
playing a perfect piano concerto.
If you choke on tests or
in public speaking,
overlearning can be especially valuable.
Did you know that even expert
public speakers practice on
the order of 70 hours 40 for
a typical 20 minute TED talk?
Automaticity can indeed be helpful
in times of nervousness, but
be wary of repetitive overlearning
during a single session.
Research has shown it can be
a waste of valuable learning time.
The reality is, once you've got
the basic idea down during a session,
continuing to hammer away at it during the
same session doesn't strengthen the kinds
of long term memory connections
you want to have strengthened.
Worse yet, focusing on one technique
is a little like learning carpentry.
By only practicing with
a hammer after a while,
you think you can fix anything
by just bashing at it.
Using a subsequent study session to repeat
what you're trying to learn is just fine
and often valuable.
It can strengthen and
deepen your chunked neural patterns.
But be wary.
Repeating something you already know
perfectly well is, face it, easy.
It can also bring the illusion of
competence that you've mastered the full
range of material when you've actually
only mastered the easy stuff.
Instead, you want to balance your
studies by deliberately focusing on
what you find more difficult.
This focusing on the more difficult
material is called deliberate practice.
It's often what makes the difference
between a good student and
a great student.
All this is also related to
a concept known as Einstellung.
In this phenomenon, your initial simple
thought, an idea you already have in mind,
or a neural pattern you've
already developed and
strengthened may prevent a better idea or
solution from being found.
We saw this in the focused pinball
picture where your initial
pinball thought went to
the upper part of the brain, but
the solution thought pattern
was in the lower part.
The crowded bumpers of
the focused mode and
the previous patterns you've built can
create a sort of rut that prevents
you from springing to a new place
where the solution might be found.
Incidentally, the German word
Einstellung means mindset.
Basically, you can remember Einstellung
as installing a roadblock because of
the way you were initially
looking at something.
This kind of wrong approach is
especially easy to do in sports and
science, not to mention other disciplines,
because sometimes your initial
intuition about what's happening or
what you need to be doing is misleading.
You have to unlearn your
erroneous older ideas or
approaches even even while
you're learning new ones.
One significant mistake students sometimes
make in learning is jumping into the water
before they learn to swim.
In other words, they blindly start working
on homework without reading the textbook,
attending lectures,
viewing online lessons, or
even speaking with someone knowledgeable.
This is a recipe for sinking it's
like randomly allowing a thought to
kind of pop off in the focus mode
pinball machine without paying any
real attention to where
the solution truly lies.
Understanding how to obtain real solutions
is important in learning and in life.
Mastering a new subject means learning
not only the basic chunks, but
also learning how to select and
use different chunks.
The best way to learn that is by
practicing jumping back and forth between
problems or situations that require
different techniques or strategies.
This is called interleaving.
Once you have the basic idea of a
technique down during your study session,
sort of like learning to ride
a bike with training wheels,
start interleaving your practice
with problems of different types or
different types of approaches,
concepts, or procedures.
Sometimes this can be
a little tough to do.
A given section in a book, for example,
is often devoted to a specific technique,
so when you flip to that section,
you already know which technique
you're going to be using.
Still, do what you can
to mix up your learning.
In science and math in particular, it can
help to look ahead at the more varied
problem sets that are sometimes
found at the end of chapters.
Or you can deliberately try to make
yourself occasionally pick out why some
problems call for
one technique as opposed to another.
You want your brain to become used to
the idea that just knowing how to use
a particular concept, approach, or
problem solving technique isn't enough.
You also need to know when to use it.
Interleaving your studies, making it
a point to review for a test, for
example, by skipping around through
problems in the different chapters and
materials, can sometimes seem to make
your learning a little more difficult,
but in reality,
it helps you learn more deeply.
Interleaving is extraordinarily important.
Although practice and
repetition is important in helping
build solid neural patterns to draw on,
it's interleaving that starts
building flexibility and creativity.
It's where you leave the world
of practice and repetition and
begin thinking more independently.
When you interleave within one subject or
one discipline,
you begin to develop your creative
power within that discipline.
When you interleave between several
subjects or disciplines, you can easily,
more easily, make interesting new
connections between chunks in
the different fields, which can
enhance your creativity even further.
Of course, it takes time to develop solid
chunks of knowledge in different fields,
so sometimes there's a trade off.
Developing expertise in
several fields means you
can bring very new ideas
from one field to the other.
But it can also mean that your expertise
in one field or the other isn't quite as
deep as that of the person who
specializes in only one discipline.
On the other hand, if you develop
expertise in only one discipline,
you you may know it very deeply, but
you may become more deeply entrenched
in your familiar ways of thinking and
not be able to handle new ideas.
Philosopher of science Thomas Kuhn
discovered that most paradigm shifts
in science are brought about
by either young people or
people who were originally trained
in a different discipline.
They're not so
easily trapped by Einstellung blocked
thoughts due to their preceding training.
And of course, there's the old saying
that science progresses one funeral at
a time as people entrenched in the old
ways of looking at things die off.
Finally, don't make the mistake of
thinking that learning only occurs in
the kinds of subjects you
acquire from teachers or books.
When you teach a child how to
deal effectively with a bully,
or you fix a leaky faucet,
or you quickly pack a small suitcase for
a business trip to Hong Kong,
all of these illustrate the outcomes
of important aspects of learning.
Physicist, Richard Feynman was inspired
in his Nobel Prize winning work by
watching someone throw a dinner
plate into the air in a cafeteria.
And Mike Rowe of the television show's
Dirty Jobs and Somebody's Got to Do it,
shows how important and exciting how
exciting learning can be in a variety of
different nonacademic disciplines.
I'm Barbara Oakley.
Thanks for learning about learning.